<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philsoc on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/series/philsoc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philsoc on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/philsoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Elmo, the Cookie Monster, and Epistemic Injustice</title>
      <link>/2020/05/20/elmo-the-cookie-monster-and-epistemic-injustice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/20/elmo-the-cookie-monster-and-epistemic-injustice/</guid>
      <description>Last night at Philsoc I had cause to bring up a fascinating piece of research.
&amp;#8853; Jackson J.E., Green L. (2005) Tense and Aspectual be in Child African American English. In: Verkuyl H.J., de Swart H., van Hout A. (eds) Perspectives on Aspect. Studies in Theoretical Psycholinguistics, vol 32. Springer, Dordrecht  Janice E. Jackson and Lisa Green conducted research on a group of primary school students in Massachusetts. Some of the students were white, some black.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Veil of Ignorance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</guid>
      <description>It’s a Philosophy Society day today, and we are going to be talking about justice and fairness. I’ve sent round some readings from Rawls and Nozick, and I’ll use this writing session as a bit of a refresher. I’m just gonna focus on Rawls though.
Rawls is inspired by Locke, in the sense that he finds his idea of ‘natural’ or ‘basic’ and ‘inalienable’ rights attractive and wants to retain that concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immortality and Change in Doctor Who</title>
      <link>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</guid>
      <description>One of the few benefits of lockdown is reconnecting with old friends. My university Philsoc, who have made a couple of attempts at meeting up again to socialise, have realised that in fact we can use Zoom to just flat-out meet up and talk about philosophy once a fortnight. It’s the third meeting tonight, the topic is Immortality, and there is no set reading this time. So today’s entry is a two-for-one: I’m going to use my writing practice to prepare some thoughts for tonight’s meeting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>