<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Self Improvement on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/categories/self-improvement/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Self Improvement on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/self-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Article-A-Day Challenge</title>
      <link>/2020/07/01/the-article-a-day-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/01/the-article-a-day-challenge/</guid>
      <description>A recommendation/challenge has emerged from Dr Olivia Rissland on Twitter to read one academic article a day and keep a record of it
On Jan 1, 2018, I decided to read more papers and started trying to read a paper a day. As of today, I have read 899 papers in 899 days. I never would have imagined 2.5 years ago how much I would learn through this and how this would make me a better scientist and human.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</guid>
      <description>As I said at the end of May, I plan for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. This is my list for June.
NovelsThe Hollow Lands (Dancers at the End of Time part II), Michael MoorcockIn which Jherek Carnelian continues to be in love with Mrs. Amelia Underwood, travels to nineteenth century London to find her, accidentally becomes a criminal, doesn’t die, and continues with Various Adventures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Badly; or Goodhart’s Law</title>
      <link>/2020/06/28/reading-badly-or-goodharts-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/28/reading-badly-or-goodharts-law/</guid>
      <description>Lockdown has produced in me, as it has in many people, a certain urge to Use the Time for Self-Improvement. This has, amongst other things, included a significant up-swing in the amount of reading I’ve done. I was very much a reader when I was younger, but a combination of parenting a small child, an obligation to read a lot for work, and the ease of screentime, have drastically diminished the amount I read for recreation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</guid>
      <description>My plan is for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. I’m not going to attempt anything significant in terms of reviews unless the mood takes me, but I’ll include at least a line or two of description.This is what I’ve read in May:
NovelsConfessions of the Fox, Jordy Rosenburg.Compellingly strange, half written in footnotes, this is two novels in one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>