<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How Not to Think Like Sherlock Holmes on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/series/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in How Not to Think Like Sherlock Holmes on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Three]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/22/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-three/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/22/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-three/</guid>
      <description>Holmes’ approach to reasoning can be summed up in the famous phrase:
‘When you have eliminated all which is impossible, then whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.’
This is known as the Holmesian Fallacy, and there are a number of ways in which it is wrong.
A. It requires you to identify every potential explanation for the observed phenomenon,
B. It requires you to demonstrate that all but one of those is impossible,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Two]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</guid>
      <description>So yesterday I analysed the argumentative structure of a section of the argument put forward by Sherlock in the Study in Pink. One of the purposes of this exercise was to illustrate various argument structures: it’s a good way of demonstrating what deduction actually is, what deductively valid and deductively sound arguments are, and what inductively forceful arguments are. The other purpose, however, was to illustrate the discrepancy between how good Sherlock’s arguments are perceived to be by others, and how good they actually are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part One]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/08/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/08/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-one/</guid>
      <description>I used to teach an informal logic class at a small university not far from Baker Street Station, and there is basically no way to be in that exact situation and not make some use of Sherlock Holmes. At the moment I’m expanding on the materials I used there to create a four-week online course, and also a corporate workshop (the latter obviously being for the After Times). I’m gonna use this format to play with some of the ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>