<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>drabble on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/series/drabble/</link>
    <description>Recent content in drabble on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/drabble/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Gettier</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/drabble-gettier/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/drabble-gettier/</guid>
      <description>In his influential article “Is Justified True Belief Knowledge?”, Gettier offers examples of justified true beliefs which don’t appear to be knowledge. My own invented ‘Gettier’ problem: suppose that you are on a high street where unbeknownest to you, an Autons episode of Doctor Who is about to be filmed. You believe you’re looking at a mannequin, it’s true that you are, and the belief is justified (this shop window usually has mannequins in it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Kuhnian Incommensurability</title>
      <link>/2020/06/04/drabble-kuhnian-incommensurability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/04/drabble-kuhnian-incommensurability/</guid>
      <description>Thomas Kuhn, in the Structure of Scientific Revolutions, suggests the science does not accumulate knowledge in a linear way. Instead there are periods of ‘normal science’, in which scientists work within a paradigm (e.g. Newtonian physics) to solve puzzles. Eventually anomalous results build up which challenge the paradigm, but scientists are not inclined to abandon the paradigm unless a rival paradigm is available. A scientist adopting a new paradigm is a radical intellectual shift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Merleau-Ponty</title>
      <link>/2020/05/30/drabble-merleau-ponty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/30/drabble-merleau-ponty/</guid>
      <description>In the Phenomenology of Perception, Merleau-Ponty rejects Cartesian dualism. He explores the case of a First World War veteran, Schneider, who suffered a brain injury caused by shrapnel. Schneider wasn’t paralysed, but he was disconnected from his own body. He lost proprioception, and had to look at, find, his limbs before moving them. He operated his body from the inside, as though it were a machine. Merleau-Ponty contrasts Schneider’s experience of his body and the more typical experience to demonstrate that our bodies are not machines operated by the brain, that they aren’t in fact objects at all, but subjects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - The Problem of Induction and Falsificationism</title>
      <link>/2020/05/29/drabble-the-problem-of-induction-and-falsificationism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/29/drabble-the-problem-of-induction-and-falsificationism/</guid>
      <description>The Problem of Induction, initially presented by David Hume, is that since scientific knowledge is founded on experience, we are not justified in believing that the causal patterns we have thus far witnessed will continue in the future, or that they apply in parts of space we have not directly observed. Proving scientific theories to be true is therefore impossible. Karl Popper responds by arguing that the distinctive feature of scientific claims is not that they can be verified but that they can be falsified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Hume’s Fork</title>
      <link>/2020/05/24/drabble-humes-fork/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/24/drabble-humes-fork/</guid>
      <description>Hume’s Fork divides ‘relations of ideas’ from ‘matters of fact’. Relations of ideas are things we know to be true because of how concepts relate to each other, and we know them by understanding the concepts (e.g. ‘bachelors are unmarried’.) &amp;#8853; I once knew a lecturer, who in a desire to be mildly original, changed this classic example to ‘every husband has a wife’. No one told him.  Matters of fact are true because of how the world is, and we know them through experience of the world (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Aristotle’s Ethics</title>
      <link>/2020/05/23/drabble-aristotles-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/23/drabble-aristotles-ethics/</guid>
      <description>For the uninitiated, a ‘drabble’ is a work of fiction of exactly 100 words long, which is intended to test the writer’s ability to express interesting ideas in a confined space. I am experimenting here with using the format to explain philosophical concepts. This may become something I use as writing prompts for days when I am short of time and spoons.
(This isn’t the drabble yet. The next paragraph is the drabble.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>