<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Locke’s Conduct of the Understanding: A Translation Section Two</title>
      <link>/2020/10/14/lockes-conduct-of-the-understanding-a-translation-section-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/14/lockes-conduct-of-the-understanding-a-translation-section-two/</guid>
      <description>The project continues! Just a short one today.
Section II. Parts. 
Original TextThere is, it is visible, great variety in men’s understandings, and their natural constitutions put so wide a difference between some men in this respect, that art and industry would never be able to master; and their natures seem to want a foundation to raise on it that which other men easily attain to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locke’s Conduct of the Understanding: A Translation Section One</title>
      <link>/2020/09/19/lockes-conduct-of-the-understanding-a-translation-section-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/19/lockes-conduct-of-the-understanding-a-translation-section-one/</guid>
      <description>I’ve got a new blog project which should provide me with some shortish, simpleish writing exercises for some time to come. I intend to write a translation of Locke’s Conduct of the Understanding. Now obviously Locke wrote in English, but in seventeenth century English, which I am given to understand is not as easy a read for most people as it is for me. So I’m going to go through section by section and re-write it into modern English.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Truthful Lies</title>
      <link>/2020/09/07/truthful-lies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/07/truthful-lies/</guid>
      <description>Imagine the following scenario: a teacher, talking to her class of six-year-olds about the solar system, explains that the sun is made of burning gas.
However, the teacher is sufficiently knowledgeable about physics to be aware that, in fact, the sun is composed of plasma. The electrons in plasma are not bound to the nucleus as they are in a gas, so plasma is a fourth state of matter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Contrasting Epistemic Approaches of Thales of Miletus and the Insane Clown Posse</title>
      <link>/2020/08/20/the-contrasting-epistemic-approaches-of-thales-of-miletus-and-the-insane-clown-posse/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/20/the-contrasting-epistemic-approaches-of-thales-of-miletus-and-the-insane-clown-posse/</guid>
      <description>I’ve spoken before about falsificationism and foundherentism, but I’ve recently noticed a rather lovely contrast between the epistemic approaches of Thales of Miletus and the Insane Clown Posse which illustrates both pretty well.
So to start, here’s a brief refresher. Falsificationism, as put forward by Karl Popper, is the idea that science doesn’t advance by conjectures being proven correct, but by them being falsified; or else by our best attempts to falsify them failing, at which point we can be justified in treating the conjectures as true - although we haven’t proven them to be true, as they may later turn out to be false.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joseph Merrick, and the Privilege of Telling Your Own Story</title>
      <link>/2020/08/19/joseph-merrick-and-the-privilege-of-telling-your-own-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/19/joseph-merrick-and-the-privilege-of-telling-your-own-story/</guid>
      <description>I met Joseph Merrick the way most people do, which is via the David Lynch film adaptation The Elephant Man; in my case closely followed by reading the original text it was based on, namely The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences by Dr. Frederick Treves. The film adaptation follows Treves’ account relatively faithfully in spirit, although it does swap around the order of events for dramatic effect, and give Merrick a far more comprehensible speaking voice than he actually had (for understandable practical reasons) and with it an inexplicably middle-class accent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Urgh’ Fields and ‘Argh’ Fields</title>
      <link>/2020/08/02/urgh-fields-and-argh-fields/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/02/urgh-fields-and-argh-fields/</guid>
      <description>My online course ‘How Not To Think Like Sherlock Holmes’ has finally started. This is based on an idea that I had years ago, that I’ve invested quite a lot in, in bits and pieces over time, and the fact that it’s finally underway feels like kind of a big deal. The strange thing is that it shouldn’t be a big deal. Teaching an online class of this kind is well within my abilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>July Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/07/31/july-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/31/july-reading/</guid>
      <description>Here’s what I’ve been reading in July:
Novels
The Passion, Jeanette Winterson
It’s atmospheric and poetic and sensual and basically it’s Written on the Body again, but with Bonaparte and Venecian boatmen, and it leads me to believe that Winterson has a thing for women with red hair. I liked it, but it’s possible that I needed a longer gap after reading Written on the Body in order to enjoy it properly, because I was very aware of the similarities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting and Procrastination</title>
      <link>/2020/07/26/painting-and-procrastination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/26/painting-and-procrastination/</guid>
      <description>Houseboats need paint. They need quite a lot of paint, quite often. I got some advice when I first bought the boat: figure out how much you can get done in an hour, or half an hour, including setting up your equipment and cleaning it and putting it away. Do this because you will often have an hour to paint, but you will far less often have a day to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philosophy and Therapy</title>
      <link>/2020/07/21/philosophy-and-therapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/21/philosophy-and-therapy/</guid>
      <description>I find the relationship between philosophy and therapy fascinating, problematic, and potentially dangerous. First let’s unpack what the relationship is, and I’ll show you what I mean.
Firstly, and least controversially in my view, there are qualified therapists who openly use philosophy as part of their toolkit. The most typical example of this is existentialist psychotherapy, which draws on existentialist philosophical texts, and frames client’s experiences around ‘existential anxiety’ about freedom and responsibility, death, isolation, and meaning/meaninglessness .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is this Blog For, Again?</title>
      <link>/2020/07/16/what-is-this-blog-for-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/16/what-is-this-blog-for-again/</guid>
      <description>Forgive the self-indulgence of this entry. I am genuinely trying to work out the answer to this question.
I, like many, adopted this notebook blog inspired by David MacIver, who makes a convincing case for the value of writing daily. This blog was initially intended to be a daily blog, and for the first month, full of enthusiasm for a new project, it almost was. The intensity has dialled down a bit since.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Five]</title>
      <link>/2020/07/15/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-five/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/15/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-five/</guid>
      <description>In Part Three of this series, I illustrated the problems with the classic Holmesian claim that ‘when you have eliminated all which is impossible, then whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.’ Douglas Adams’ position that we might in fact be more justified in believing the ‘impossible’ than the extremely improbable, rests on the idea that to believe the ‘impossible’ is simply to believe that there is something we don’t know about, that there are layers to this that don’t meet the eye.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On not bullshitting about ‘On Bullshit’ </title>
      <link>/2020/07/12/on-not-bullshitting-about-on-bullshit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/12/on-not-bullshitting-about-on-bullshit/</guid>
      <description>Ivo Wever (@Confusionist) offered the following objection to yesterday’s post:
Could Krauss be ‘sincere, inconsistent and wrong’ instead of ‘a bullshitter’? He may not have realized he had given insufficient thought to the matter until strongly challenged? If motivation doesn’t matter, aren’t we all bullshitters at times?
&amp;mdash; Ivo Wever (@Confusionist) July 9, 2020  Could Krauss be ‘sincere, inconsistent and wrong’ instead of ‘a bullshitter’? He may not have realized he had given insufficient thought to the matter until strongly challenged?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harry G. Frankfurt’s ‘On Bullshit,’ and the Epistemic Standards of Philosophy</title>
      <link>/2020/07/09/harry-g.-frankfurts-on-bullshit-and-the-epistemic-standards-of-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/09/harry-g.-frankfurts-on-bullshit-and-the-epistemic-standards-of-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Ever wake up in the morning having an imaginary intellectual argument with an imaginary person in which you are definitely right? This is a very literal version of ‘phantom opinions’ and it happens to me all the time. Most of my greatest intellectual successes occur in this world. I am astonishingly convincing.
Let’s test one of them here to see if it actually works, though.
So. Philosophy sometimes takes a battering from the scientific/rationalist/new-atheist crowd for, essentially, not being science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Kant’s Categorical Imperative</title>
      <link>/2020/07/04/drabble-kants-categorical-imperative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/04/drabble-kants-categorical-imperative/</guid>
      <description>Kant’s two formulations of the categorical imperative are:
“Act only according to that maxim by which you can at the same time will that it should become a universal law”.“Act in such a way that you treat humanity, whether in your own person or in the person of another, always at the same time as an end and never simply as a means.”In order for your actions to be moral, you have to be able to rationally desire a world where everyone would act in this way, and you have to treat people (including yourself) as intrinsically valuable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Article-A-Day Challenge</title>
      <link>/2020/07/01/the-article-a-day-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/01/the-article-a-day-challenge/</guid>
      <description>A recommendation/challenge has emerged from Dr Olivia Rissland on Twitter to read one academic article a day and keep a record of it
On Jan 1, 2018, I decided to read more papers and started trying to read a paper a day. As of today, I have read 899 papers in 899 days. I never would have imagined 2.5 years ago how much I would learn through this and how this would make me a better scientist and human.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</guid>
      <description>As I said at the end of May, I plan for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. This is my list for June.
NovelsThe Hollow Lands (Dancers at the End of Time part II), Michael MoorcockIn which Jherek Carnelian continues to be in love with Mrs. Amelia Underwood, travels to nineteenth century London to find her, accidentally becomes a criminal, doesn’t die, and continues with Various Adventures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Mary Healy on Children’s Friendships</title>
      <link>/2020/06/29/drabble-mary-healy-on-childrens-friendships/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/29/drabble-mary-healy-on-childrens-friendships/</guid>
      <description>In Should we take the friendships of children seriously?, Healy presents the three forms of Aristotelian friendship. Firstly: ‘friendships of utility’, which perform a function, such as ‘someone to play with’. Secondly: ‘friendships of pleasure’, deeply felt and yet often transitory: whilst you enjoy their presence, you don’t regret their absence. Finally there are ‘character friendships’: committed friendships where the flourishing of one friend is interconnected with the flourishing of the other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Badly; or Goodhart’s Law</title>
      <link>/2020/06/28/reading-badly-or-goodharts-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/28/reading-badly-or-goodharts-law/</guid>
      <description>Lockdown has produced in me, as it has in many people, a certain urge to Use the Time for Self-Improvement. This has, amongst other things, included a significant up-swing in the amount of reading I’ve done. I was very much a reader when I was younger, but a combination of parenting a small child, an obligation to read a lot for work, and the ease of screentime, have drastically diminished the amount I read for recreation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phantom Opinions</title>
      <link>/2020/06/22/phantom-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/22/phantom-opinions/</guid>
      <description>I am going to do something deeply uncharacteristic here. I’m going to coin a term for a fallacy. Yes yes, I know, but consistency is the enemy even here. Whilst I maintain that being able to describe this argumentative problem is better than being able to name it, perhaps the existence of a name is nonetheless a hermeneutical tool of some use. Let’s find out.
There is a phrase I keep coming across, in conversation, in student essays, and sometimes even in academic papers, which goes something like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marking and Modesty</title>
      <link>/2020/06/20/marking-and-modesty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/20/marking-and-modesty/</guid>
      <description>As someone with a philosophy background who has recently come to work in an education department, I am teaching - and more recently, marking papers - in areas that I am not an expert in myself. This wasn’t such an issue in the first term, as I was teaching one general introduction/student skills course, and one philosophy of education course. It was relatively straightforward to adapt to these. However, one of the courses I am marking this term requires me to assess research portfolios including a semi-structured interview.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unknown Knowns</title>
      <link>/2020/06/18/unknown-knowns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/18/unknown-knowns/</guid>
      <description>The concept of unknown unknowns is something that I will come back to in the last section of my Sherlock series, but for now I’m just going to give it a brief spell in the spotlight by itself, and introduce a related concept of my own: ‘unknown knowns’.
The phrase ‘unknown unknowns’ comes from a response that Donald Rumsfeld gave to a question put to him at a US Department of Defence news briefing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being Inconsistent about Consistency</title>
      <link>/2020/06/15/being-inconsistent-about-consistency/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/15/being-inconsistent-about-consistency/</guid>
      <description>Something odd is happening to me. I seem to be developing routines.
(This is a young and delicate flower and may not live long, I make no promises whatsoever).
Now, I hate routines. One reason I hate them because of how easily they can fail. Particularly they can fail if you are a parent. It is not possible to predict when a child will ask for help, a snack, or just generally some attention, so if you are committed to doing certain things in a certain order (self-care routines, housework, working from home) then you will be perpetually frustrated by your inability to do so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Four]</title>
      <link>/2020/06/14/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-four/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/14/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-four/</guid>
      <description>The latest in my ongoing project to ruin Sherlock Holmes’ reputation: Holmes tries to think by himself, and this is a terrible idea.
The longer way of saying this is that Holmes’ reasoning skills are compromised by his epistemic isolation. This comes in two forms. The first is an extreme degree of specialisation, accompanied by a more general ignorance (which he deliberately chooses). The second, connected issue is the social isolation that arises from his ‘solitary genius’ status, which prevents him benefiting from full membership in an epistemic community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Susan Haack’s Foundherentism</title>
      <link>/2020/06/11/drabble-susan-haacks-foundherentism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/11/drabble-susan-haacks-foundherentism/</guid>
      <description>Foundationalism holds that certain beliefs are self-evident. Other beliefs are justified with reference to these. According to coherentism, foundational beliefs don’t exist. Instead beliefs justify each other, like puzzle pieces fitting together. Haack argues that scientific investigation actually progresses like completing a crossword puzzle: it needs foundations (observations) and coherence (an overall theory). You read the clue (look at the results of your experiment), and complete the answer. If it doesn’t fit with other answers already completed, first check the clue again (for a potential anomaly); only then check the accuracy of the other answers (overall theory).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Gettier</title>
      <link>/2020/06/08/drabble-gettier/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/08/drabble-gettier/</guid>
      <description>In his influential article “Is Justified True Belief Knowledge?”, Gettier offers examples of justified true beliefs which don’t appear to be knowledge. My own invented ‘Gettier’ problem: suppose that you are on a high street where unbeknownest to you, an Autons episode of Doctor Who is about to be filmed. You believe you’re looking at a mannequin, it’s true that you are, and the belief is justified (this shop window usually has mannequins in it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Nothing Personal</title>
      <link>/2020/06/07/its-nothing-personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/07/its-nothing-personal/</guid>
      <description>I really didn’t want to write The Trouble with Lists.
This is because:
It describes a genuine problem for me. I actually do physically write these lists, and find it soothing to do so, and then (this is not made explicit in the piece but is kinda obvious) feel pressurized and frustrated afterwards. I am sufficiently inexperienced at writing in public that this feels like personal information.
The fact that nice crisp stationery is a trigger for this is really specific, and it’s weird.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Trouble with Lists</title>
      <link>/2020/06/05/the-trouble-with-lists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/05/the-trouble-with-lists/</guid>
      <description>I find the physical act of handwriting soothing. Typing is more efficient and I can keep track of my work better once I’ve done it, but for some things only pen and paper will do. Preferably, WhSmiths A4 narrow-lined paper, and a Uniball Eye Fine pen in black. Wide-lined paper will do at a pinch, but if forced to use a standard ballpoint I will do so with displeasure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Kuhnian Incommensurability</title>
      <link>/2020/06/04/drabble-kuhnian-incommensurability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/04/drabble-kuhnian-incommensurability/</guid>
      <description>Thomas Kuhn, in the Structure of Scientific Revolutions, suggests the science does not accumulate knowledge in a linear way. Instead there are periods of ‘normal science’, in which scientists work within a paradigm (e.g. Newtonian physics) to solve puzzles. Eventually anomalous results build up which challenge the paradigm, but scientists are not inclined to abandon the paradigm unless a rival paradigm is available. A scientist adopting a new paradigm is a radical intellectual shift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justified True Belief in Education</title>
      <link>/2020/06/01/justified-true-belief-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/01/justified-true-belief-in-education/</guid>
      <description>I find the thought of doing epistemology without talking about education faintly bizarre. Theory of knowledge, even at its most abstract, seems so deeply connected to theories of learning that it surprises me how distinct the fields are in practice. For this piece I’m going to play around with the traditional, tripartite definition of knowledge just to see how each of the three elements maps onto educational practices.
&amp;#8853;Note, I am well aware of the limitations of the tripartite definition of knowledge, and not only because of Gettier but it’s not not useful and it’s fun to play with it here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</guid>
      <description>My plan is for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. I’m not going to attempt anything significant in terms of reviews unless the mood takes me, but I’ll include at least a line or two of description.This is what I’ve read in May:
NovelsConfessions of the Fox, Jordy Rosenburg.Compellingly strange, half written in footnotes, this is two novels in one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Merleau-Ponty</title>
      <link>/2020/05/30/drabble-merleau-ponty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/30/drabble-merleau-ponty/</guid>
      <description>In the Phenomenology of Perception, Merleau-Ponty rejects Cartesian dualism. He explores the case of a First World War veteran, Schneider, who suffered a brain injury caused by shrapnel. Schneider wasn’t paralysed, but he was disconnected from his own body. He lost proprioception, and had to look at, find, his limbs before moving them. He operated his body from the inside, as though it were a machine. Merleau-Ponty contrasts Schneider’s experience of his body and the more typical experience to demonstrate that our bodies are not machines operated by the brain, that they aren’t in fact objects at all, but subjects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - The Problem of Induction and Falsificationism</title>
      <link>/2020/05/29/drabble-the-problem-of-induction-and-falsificationism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/29/drabble-the-problem-of-induction-and-falsificationism/</guid>
      <description>The Problem of Induction, initially presented by David Hume, is that since scientific knowledge is founded on experience, we are not justified in believing that the causal patterns we have thus far witnessed will continue in the future, or that they apply in parts of space we have not directly observed. Proving scientific theories to be true is therefore impossible. Karl Popper responds by arguing that the distinctive feature of scientific claims is not that they can be verified but that they can be falsified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fallacy Fallacy</title>
      <link>/2020/05/28/the-fallacy-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/28/the-fallacy-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my last post, I’m fond of informal logic. However I’m aware that as a field, informal logic can suffer from its formal logic ancestry. Philosophers who cut their teeth on notation may wish to translate the skill into assessing ordinary language arguments, but they may drag too much formality along with them. Notably, there is a temptation to focus on fallacies. Teachers like them because they are neat and tidy and easy to test on; students like them because they have a favourable effort-to-‘feeling clever’ ratio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great Shallows of Philosophy</title>
      <link>/2020/05/26/the-great-shallows-of-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/26/the-great-shallows-of-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>I have a comfort zone in philosophy: epistemology and ethics. Within those, I like my questions pretty applied. I like questions about the nature of knowledge; but I immediately want to relate them to questions about good and bad ways of pursuing knowledge (philosophy of science and social science) or disseminating it (philosophy of education, social epistemology). I am interested in ethics, but I prefer applied ethics, where you are trying to solve particular ethical problems and bring in different ethical systems as tools to do it, to ‘straight’ ethics, which involves studying the systems themselves in great depth - especially as the subtext of such study is often ‘choose between these,’ and consistency is the enemy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Hume’s Fork</title>
      <link>/2020/05/24/drabble-humes-fork/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/24/drabble-humes-fork/</guid>
      <description>Hume’s Fork divides ‘relations of ideas’ from ‘matters of fact’. Relations of ideas are things we know to be true because of how concepts relate to each other, and we know them by understanding the concepts (e.g. ‘bachelors are unmarried’.) &amp;#8853;I once knew a lecturer, who in a desire to be mildly original, changed this classic example to ‘every husband has a wife’. No one told him. Matters of fact are true because of how the world is, and we know them through experience of the world (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble - Aristotle’s Ethics</title>
      <link>/2020/05/23/drabble-aristotles-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/23/drabble-aristotles-ethics/</guid>
      <description>For the uninitiated, a ‘drabble’ is a work of fiction of exactly 100 words long, which is intended to test the writer’s ability to express interesting ideas in a confined space. I am experimenting here with using the format to explain philosophical concepts. This may become something I use as writing prompts for days when I am short of time and spoons.
(This isn’t the drabble yet. The next paragraph is the drabble.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Three]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/22/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-three/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/22/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-three/</guid>
      <description>Holmes’ approach to reasoning can be summed up in the famous phrase:
‘When you have eliminated all which is impossible, then whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.’
This is known as the Holmesian Fallacy, and there are a number of ways in which it is wrong.
A. It requires you to identify every potential explanation for the observed phenomenon,
B. It requires you to demonstrate that all but one of those is impossible,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elmo, the Cookie Monster, and Epistemic Injustice</title>
      <link>/2020/05/20/elmo-the-cookie-monster-and-epistemic-injustice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/20/elmo-the-cookie-monster-and-epistemic-injustice/</guid>
      <description>Last night at Philsoc I had cause to bring up a fascinating piece of research.
&amp;#8853;Jackson J.E., Green L. (2005) Tense and Aspectual be in Child African American English. In: Verkuyl H.J., de Swart H., van Hout A. (eds) Perspectives on Aspect. Studies in Theoretical Psycholinguistics, vol 32. Springer, Dordrecht Janice E. Jackson and Lisa Green conducted research on a group of primary school students in Massachusetts. Some of the students were white, some black.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Veil of Ignorance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</guid>
      <description>It’s a Philosophy Society day today, and we are going to be talking about justice and fairness. I’ve sent round some readings from Rawls and Nozick, and I’ll use this writing session as a bit of a refresher. I’m just gonna focus on Rawls though.
Rawls is inspired by Locke, in the sense that he finds his idea of ‘natural’ or ‘basic’ and ‘inalienable’ rights attractive and wants to retain that concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helen Longino on Cognitively Optimal Communities</title>
      <link>/2020/05/17/helen-longino-on-cognitively-optimal-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/17/helen-longino-on-cognitively-optimal-communities/</guid>
      <description>Helen Longino is a social epistemologist and a philosopher of science, interested in establishing what it takes for the consensus of a research group to count as knowledge. According to Longino, knowledge ‘is constructed not by individuals, but by an interactive dialogic community’ (Longino 1994: 143). In short, knowledge arises from dialogue, but not just any form of dialogue. The interactions between members of a cognitive community must amount to ‘genuine and mutual checks’ if the group’s enquiries are to be objective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being an Expert Novice</title>
      <link>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</guid>
      <description>Parenthood sucks for hobbies. The first few years of a child’s life are overwhelming in the focus that they demand from you. It’s very easy to lose things, small and significant, which are part of who you are. So a few months ago, I began something of a reclamation project. This was a conscious effort to reclaim things that used to bring me joy and which I had somewhat abandoned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testimony and Received Opinion</title>
      <link>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</guid>
      <description>I am something of an apologist for Locke. An archetypal empiricist, Locke believes that all the knowledge we have is gained through our experiences; either through sensations, or through reflections upon sensations. This seems broadly intuitively true to the modern ear. (The alternative, that some knowledge is innate, is not actually disproved by Locke in the Essay Concerning Human Understanding, but it is discredited by providing an alternative, empiricist explanation for all the knowledge we have.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tom Yum-ish Soup</title>
      <link>/2020/05/14/tom-yum-ish-soup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/14/tom-yum-ish-soup/</guid>
      <description>We bought way too much food for my daughter’s birthday. We ended up surrounded by a dangerous amount of leftover sandwiches and cake. Then after she was asleep, I had a watch party with friends. The sensible thing would have been to gather a sort of picnic dinner. It was, however, the last thing I wanted. I was craving vegetables, I was craving spice, and if I was going to have anything like that, I needed to make it in a short enough time that I wouldn’t miss much of the watch party.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge by Acquaintance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/13/knowledge-by-acquaintance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/13/knowledge-by-acquaintance/</guid>
      <description>A computer told me to take a degree in philosophy.
Seriously. When I was doing my ‘A’ levels, my school handed out a multiple choice quiz for us to complete about our interests and preferences, which was intended to help us choose a university degree. The quizzes were read and analyzed electronically and recommendations were sent back to us. My second hit was English Literature, which was no surprise, since I was doing an ‘A’ level in that, and had got an A at GCSE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decisions, Decisions</title>
      <link>/2020/05/12/decisions-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/12/decisions-decisions/</guid>
      <description>There is a trope common in popular culture about making decisions. It goes like this:
Girlfriend: I’m hungry.
Boyfriend: What would you like to eat?
Girlfriend: I don’t mind, you choose.
Boyfriend: Mexican?
Girlfriend: No, not Mexican, actually. I’m not in the mood for anything spicy.
Boyfriend: Pizza, then?
Girlfriend: Mmm, maybe not?
&amp;#8853;This particular dynamic is super-gendered in the popular imagination so I’ve left that in place here, although I’m uncertain how gendered it actually is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on a Birthday</title>
      <link>/2020/05/11/thoughts-on-a-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/11/thoughts-on-a-birthday/</guid>
      <description>They warn you, before your child is even born, about the lasts.
The last time they fit into those ‘newborn’ sized baby clothes which you will stare at, confused, six months later when your definition of ‘small’ has changed. The last time they fit neatly between your palm and the crook of your elbow. The last time they feed at your breast, and their now-more-tenuous connection to your body is severed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Two]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</guid>
      <description>So yesterday I analysed the argumentative structure of a section of the argument put forward by Sherlock in the Study in Pink. One of the purposes of this exercise was to illustrate various argument structures: it’s a good way of demonstrating what deduction actually is, what deductively valid and deductively sound arguments are, and what inductively forceful arguments are. The other purpose, however, was to illustrate the discrepancy between how good Sherlock’s arguments are perceived to be by others, and how good they actually are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part One]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/08/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/08/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-one/</guid>
      <description>I used to teach an informal logic class at a small university not far from Baker Street Station, and there is basically no way to be in that exact situation and not make some use of Sherlock Holmes. At the moment I’m expanding on the materials I used there to create a four-week online course, and also a corporate workshop (the latter obviously being for the After Times). I’m gonna use this format to play with some of the ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionary Road: How Not to be Interesting</title>
      <link>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</guid>
      <description>I recently re-read Revolutionary Road (say that three times fast). It’s a book I find compelling precisely because I don’t exactly connect to it. I am delighted by the manner in which I don’t connect to it. The central idea of the book is that the characters, Frank and April Wheeler, perceive themselves as more interesting than the people around them, as stifled by the oppressive conventionality of American suburbia, and as longing for escape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Should I Believe You?</title>
      <link>/2020/05/06/why-should-i-believe-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/06/why-should-i-believe-you/</guid>
      <description>Today I have a good deal of Real Work to do and so I can’t spend much time on this piece. However, even though consistency is the enemy, I’m reluctant to break my streak so soon, so I’m going to compromise with a bit of self-plagiarism.
Back in 2013 I contributed a chapter to ‘The Good Wife and Philosophy: Temptations of Saint Alicia’, part of the Popular Culture and Philosophy series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immortality and Change in Doctor Who</title>
      <link>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</guid>
      <description>One of the few benefits of lockdown is reconnecting with old friends. My university Philsoc, who have made a couple of attempts at meeting up again to socialise, have realised that in fact we can use Zoom to just flat-out meet up and talk about philosophy once a fortnight. It’s the third meeting tonight, the topic is Immortality, and there is no set reading this time. So today’s entry is a two-for-one: I’m going to use my writing practice to prepare some thoughts for tonight’s meeting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consistency is the Enemy</title>
      <link>/2020/05/04/consistency-is-the-enemy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/04/consistency-is-the-enemy/</guid>
      <description>This is my fourth daily writing exercise and I’m getting nervous. Here’s why:
I didn’t wake up with an idea of what to write here.
I’m doing this on borrowed time whilst my daughter watches Disney cartoons with headphones two metres away from me. I am uncertain how many hugs and snacks will be required before this is over, and whether I will get better or worse at this juggling act.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Houseboats as Liminal Spaces</title>
      <link>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</guid>
      <description>I like to joke that houseboats ruin all metaphors. Examples include:
Are you on board? No, but I’ll be home in a bit.
Let’s push the boat out! But we’d need to get longer standoffs and it would take all afternoon, can we not?
Wouldn’t touch you with a six foot barge pole! Well, good, it’s all covered in river goop.
I’ll show you the ropes!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Children’s Agnotological Rights in a Pandemic</title>
      <link>/2020/05/02/childrens-agnotological-rights-in-a-pandemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/02/childrens-agnotological-rights-in-a-pandemic/</guid>
      <description>I’ve published before on children’s epistemic rights. Epistemic rights are rights which pertain to knowledge. These include (not exclusively): our right to know certain things, and our right to be recognised as knowledgeable about things when we are.
Children and adults are generally given different legal rights. Whilst some radical philosophers, such as John Harris in The Political Status of Children, advocate for emancipation, believing that children should have the exact same legal rights as adults &amp;#8853;Yes, all of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beauty and Identity</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/beauty-and-identity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/beauty-and-identity/</guid>
      <description>Lockdown has me watching far too much classic Disney with my daughter. This has me thinking a lot about beauty and identity. Predictably, the movies depict a strong connection between ‘beauty’ and ‘goodness’. The leading women are, of course, very beautiful, with that beauty clearly presented as a physical manifestation of their innate goodness. Villains are generally identifiable by their ugliness. Plainness, meanwhile, is dullness; a sign that you aren’t really part of the story at all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not To Think Like Sherlock Holmes</title>
      <link>/page/sherlock/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/sherlock/</guid>
      <description>If you’ve enjoyed my posts on How Not To Think Like Sherlock Holmes you would probably also enjoy my online course, also called “How Not To Think Like Sherlock Holmes”
Come and discover the reasoning skills of the Master of Deduction. Just how does Sherlock Holmes come to his conclusions? How does he convince Scotland Yard that he is right? And is it wise of him to forget that the earth goes around the sun?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>