<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John Locke on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/refs/john-locke/</link>
    <description>Recent content in John Locke on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/refs/john-locke/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Veil of Ignorance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</guid>
      <description>It’s a Philosophy Society day today, and we are going to be talking about justice and fairness. I’ve sent round some readings from Rawls and Nozick, and I’ll use this writing session as a bit of a refresher. I’m just gonna focus on Rawls though.
Rawls is inspired by Locke, in the sense that he finds his idea of ‘natural’ or ‘basic’ and ‘inalienable’ rights attractive and wants to retain that concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being an Expert Novice</title>
      <link>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</guid>
      <description>Parenthood sucks for hobbies. The first few years of a child’s life are overwhelming in the focus that they demand from you. It’s very easy to lose things, small and significant, which are part of who you are. So a few months ago, I began something of a reclamation project. This was a conscious effort to reclaim things that used to bring me joy and which I had somewhat abandoned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testimony and Received Opinion</title>
      <link>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</guid>
      <description>I am something of an apologist for Locke. An archetypal empiricist, Locke believes that all the knowledge we have is gained through our experiences; either through sensations, or through reflections upon sensations. This seems broadly intuitively true to the modern ear. (The alternative, that some knowledge is innate, is not actually disproved by Locke in the Essay Concerning Human Understanding, but it is discredited by providing an alternative, empiricist explanation for all the knowledge we have.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Not to Think like Sherlock Holmes [Part Two]</title>
      <link>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/09/how-not-to-think-like-sherlock-holmes-part-two/</guid>
      <description>So yesterday I analysed the argumentative structure of a section of the argument put forward by Sherlock in the Study in Pink. One of the purposes of this exercise was to illustrate various argument structures: it’s a good way of demonstrating what deduction actually is, what deductively valid and deductively sound arguments are, and what inductively forceful arguments are. The other purpose, however, was to illustrate the discrepancy between how good Sherlock’s arguments are perceived to be by others, and how good they actually are.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>