<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Epistemology on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/tags/epistemology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Epistemology on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/epistemology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Drabble: Mary Healy on Children’s Friendships</title>
      <link>/2020/06/29/drabble-mary-healy-on-childrens-friendships/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/29/drabble-mary-healy-on-childrens-friendships/</guid>
      <description>In Should we take the friendships of children seriously?, Healy presents the three forms of Aristotelian friendship. Firstly: ‘friendships of utility’, which perform a function, such as ‘someone to play with’. Secondly: ‘friendships of pleasure’, deeply felt and yet often transitory: whilst you enjoy their presence, you don’t regret their absence. Finally there are ‘character friendships’: committed friendships where the flourishing of one friend is interconnected with the flourishing of the other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unknown Knowns</title>
      <link>/2020/06/18/unknown-knowns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/18/unknown-knowns/</guid>
      <description>The concept of unknown unknowns is something that I will come back to in the last section of my Sherlock series, but for now I’m just going to give it a brief spell in the spotlight by itself, and introduce a related concept of my own: ‘unknown knowns’.
The phrase ‘unknown unknowns’ comes from a response that Donald Rumsfeld gave to a question put to him at a US Department of Defence news briefing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justified True Belief in Education</title>
      <link>/2020/06/01/justified-true-belief-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/01/justified-true-belief-in-education/</guid>
      <description>I find the thought of doing epistemology without talking about education faintly bizarre. Theory of knowledge, even at its most abstract, seems so deeply connected to theories of learning that it surprises me how distinct the fields are in practice. For this piece I’m going to play around with the traditional, tripartite definition of knowledge just to see how each of the three elements maps onto educational practices.
&amp;#8853; Note, I am well aware of the limitations of the tripartite definition of knowledge, and not only because of Gettier but it’s not not useful and it’s fun to play with it here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testimony and Received Opinion</title>
      <link>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</guid>
      <description>I am something of an apologist for Locke. An archetypal empiricist, Locke believes that all the knowledge we have is gained through our experiences; either through sensations, or through reflections upon sensations. This seems broadly intuitively true to the modern ear. (The alternative, that some knowledge is innate, is not actually disproved by Locke in the Essay Concerning Human Understanding, but it is discredited by providing an alternative, empiricist explanation for all the knowledge we have.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>