<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>daily writing on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/series/daily-writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in daily writing on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/daily-writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Veil of Ignorance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/19/the-veil-of-ignorance/</guid>
      <description>It’s a Philosophy Society day today, and we are going to be talking about justice and fairness. I’ve sent round some readings from Rawls and Nozick, and I’ll use this writing session as a bit of a refresher. I’m just gonna focus on Rawls though.
Rawls is inspired by Locke, in the sense that he finds his idea of ‘natural’ or ‘basic’ and ‘inalienable’ rights attractive and wants to retain that concept.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being an Expert Novice</title>
      <link>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/16/being-an-expert-novice/</guid>
      <description>Parenthood sucks for hobbies. The first few years of a child’s life are overwhelming in the focus that they demand from you. It’s very easy to lose things, small and significant, which are part of who you are. So a few months ago, I began something of a reclamation project. This was a conscious effort to reclaim things that used to bring me joy and which I had somewhat abandoned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testimony and Received Opinion</title>
      <link>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/15/testimony-and-received-opinion/</guid>
      <description>I am something of an apologist for Locke. An archetypal empiricist, Locke believes that all the knowledge we have is gained through our experiences; either through sensations, or through reflections upon sensations. This seems broadly intuitively true to the modern ear. (The alternative, that some knowledge is innate, is not actually disproved by Locke in the Essay Concerning Human Understanding, but it is discredited by providing an alternative, empiricist explanation for all the knowledge we have.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tom Yum-ish Soup</title>
      <link>/2020/05/14/tom-yum-ish-soup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/14/tom-yum-ish-soup/</guid>
      <description>We bought way too much food for my daughter’s birthday. We ended up surrounded by a dangerous amount of leftover sandwiches and cake. Then after she was asleep, I had a watch party with friends. The sensible thing would have been to gather a sort of picnic dinner. It was, however, the last thing I wanted. I was craving vegetables, I was craving spice, and if I was going to have anything like that, I needed to make it in a short enough time that I wouldn’t miss much of the watch party.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge by Acquaintance</title>
      <link>/2020/05/13/knowledge-by-acquaintance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/13/knowledge-by-acquaintance/</guid>
      <description>A computer told me to take a degree in philosophy.
Seriously. When I was doing my ‘A’ levels, my school handed out a multiple choice quiz for us to complete about our interests and preferences, which was intended to help us choose a university degree. The quizzes were read and analyzed electronically and recommendations were sent back to us. My second hit was English Literature, which was no surprise, since I was doing an ‘A’ level in that, and had got an A at GCSE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decisions, Decisions</title>
      <link>/2020/05/12/decisions-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/12/decisions-decisions/</guid>
      <description>There is a trope common in popular culture about making decisions. It goes like this:
Girlfriend: I’m hungry.
Boyfriend: What would you like to eat?
Girlfriend: I don’t mind, you choose.
Boyfriend: Mexican?
Girlfriend: No, not Mexican, actually. I’m not in the mood for anything spicy.
Boyfriend: Pizza, then?
Girlfriend: Mmm, maybe not?
&amp;#8853; This particular dynamic is super-gendered in the popular imagination so I’ve left that in place here, although I’m uncertain how gendered it actually is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionary Road: How Not to be Interesting</title>
      <link>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</guid>
      <description>I recently re-read Revolutionary Road (say that three times fast). It’s a book I find compelling precisely because I don’t exactly connect to it. I am delighted by the manner in which I don’t connect to it. The central idea of the book is that the characters, Frank and April Wheeler, perceive themselves as more interesting than the people around them, as stifled by the oppressive conventionality of American suburbia, and as longing for escape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Should I Believe You?</title>
      <link>/2020/05/06/why-should-i-believe-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/06/why-should-i-believe-you/</guid>
      <description>Today I have a good deal of Real Work to do and so I can’t spend much time on this piece. However, even though consistency is the enemy, I’m reluctant to break my streak so soon, so I’m going to compromise with a bit of self-plagiarism.
Back in 2013 I contributed a chapter to ‘The Good Wife and Philosophy: Temptations of Saint Alicia’, part of the Popular Culture and Philosophy series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immortality and Change in Doctor Who</title>
      <link>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/05/immortality-and-change-in-doctor-who/</guid>
      <description>One of the few benefits of lockdown is reconnecting with old friends. My university Philsoc, who have made a couple of attempts at meeting up again to socialise, have realised that in fact we can use Zoom to just flat-out meet up and talk about philosophy once a fortnight. It’s the third meeting tonight, the topic is Immortality, and there is no set reading this time. So today’s entry is a two-for-one: I’m going to use my writing practice to prepare some thoughts for tonight’s meeting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consistency is the Enemy</title>
      <link>/2020/05/04/consistency-is-the-enemy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/04/consistency-is-the-enemy/</guid>
      <description>This is my fourth daily writing exercise and I’m getting nervous. Here’s why:
I didn’t wake up with an idea of what to write here.I’m doing this on borrowed time whilst my daughter watches Disney cartoons with headphones two metres away from me. I am uncertain how many hugs and snacks will be required before this is over, and whether I will get better or worse at this juggling act.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Houseboats as Liminal Spaces</title>
      <link>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</guid>
      <description>I like to joke that houseboats ruin all metaphors. Examples include:
Are you on board? No, but I’ll be home in a bit.
Let’s push the boat out! But we’d need to get longer standoffs and it would take all afternoon, can we not?
Wouldn’t touch you with a six foot barge pole! Well, good, it’s all covered in river goop.
I’ll show you the ropes!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Children’s Agnotological Rights in a Pandemic</title>
      <link>/2020/05/02/childrens-agnotological-rights-in-a-pandemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/02/childrens-agnotological-rights-in-a-pandemic/</guid>
      <description>I’ve published before on children’s epistemic rights. Epistemic rights are rights which pertain to knowledge. These include (not exclusively): our right to know certain things, and our right to be recognised as knowledgeable about things when we are.
Children and adults are generally given different legal rights. Whilst some radical philosophers, such as John Harris in The Political Status of Children, advocate for emancipation, believing that children should have the exact same legal rights as adults &amp;#8853; Yes, all of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beauty and Identity</title>
      <link>/2020/05/01/beauty-and-identity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/01/beauty-and-identity/</guid>
      <description>Lockdown has me watching far too much classic Disney with my daughter. This has me thinking a lot about beauty and identity. Predictably, the movies depict a strong connection between ‘beauty’ and ‘goodness’. The leading women are, of course, very beautiful, with that beauty clearly presented as a physical manifestation of their innate goodness. Villains are generally identifiable by their ugliness. Plainness, meanwhile, is dullness; a sign that you aren’t really part of the story at all.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>