<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reading on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/series/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reading on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/series/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>July Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/07/31/july-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/31/july-reading/</guid>
      <description>Here’s what I’ve been reading in July:
Novels
The Passion, Jeanette Winterson
It’s atmospheric and poetic and sensual and basically it’s Written on the Body again, but with Bonaparte and Venecian boatmen, and it leads me to believe that Winterson has a thing for women with red hair. I liked it, but it’s possible that I needed a longer gap after reading Written on the Body in order to enjoy it properly, because I was very aware of the similarities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>June Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/30/june-reading/</guid>
      <description>As I said at the end of May, I plan for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. This is my list for June.
NovelsThe Hollow Lands (Dancers at the End of Time part II), Michael MoorcockIn which Jherek Carnelian continues to be in love with Mrs. Amelia Underwood, travels to nineteenth century London to find her, accidentally becomes a criminal, doesn’t die, and continues with Various Adventures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May Reading</title>
      <link>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/31/may-reading/</guid>
      <description>My plan is for the last entry of every month to be a record of the reading I’ve done that month. I’m not going to attempt anything significant in terms of reviews unless the mood takes me, but I’ll include at least a line or two of description.This is what I’ve read in May:
NovelsConfessions of the Fox, Jordy Rosenburg.Compellingly strange, half written in footnotes, this is two novels in one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>