<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Houseboats on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/tags/houseboats/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Houseboats on Lisa&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/houseboats/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting and Procrastination</title>
      <link>/2020/07/26/painting-and-procrastination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/26/painting-and-procrastination/</guid>
      <description>Houseboats need paint. They need quite a lot of paint, quite often. I got some advice when I first bought the boat: figure out how much you can get done in an hour, or half an hour, including setting up your equipment and cleaning it and putting it away. Do this because you will often have an hour to paint, but you will far less often have a day to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionary Road: How Not to be Interesting</title>
      <link>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/07/revolutionary-road-how-not-to-be-interesting/</guid>
      <description>I recently re-read Revolutionary Road (say that three times fast). It’s a book I find compelling precisely because I don’t exactly connect to it. I am delighted by the manner in which I don’t connect to it. The central idea of the book is that the characters, Frank and April Wheeler, perceive themselves as more interesting than the people around them, as stifled by the oppressive conventionality of American suburbia, and as longing for escape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Houseboats as Liminal Spaces</title>
      <link>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/03/houseboats-as-liminal-spaces/</guid>
      <description>I like to joke that houseboats ruin all metaphors. Examples include:
Are you on board? No, but I’ll be home in a bit.
Let’s push the boat out! But we’d need to get longer standoffs and it would take all afternoon, can we not?
Wouldn’t touch you with a six foot barge pole! Well, good, it’s all covered in river goop.
I’ll show you the ropes!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>